<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.2//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.2/docbookx.dtd">
<book id="index" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
    <bookinfo>
	<title>Working with XML using xmlwrapp</title>
	<subtitle>A C++ Developers Guide</subtitle>

	<authorgroup>
	    <author>
		<firstname>Peter</firstname>
		<surname>Jones</surname>
		<affiliation>
		    <address>
			<email>pjones@pmade.org</email>
		    </address>
		</affiliation>
	    </author>
	</authorgroup>

	<copyright>
	    <year>2001</year>
	    <year>2002</year>
	    <year>2003</year>
	    <holder>Peter Jones (http://pmade.org/pjones/)</holder>
	</copyright>

	<legalnotice>
	    <para>
		Redistribution and use in source (SGML DocBook) and 'compiled'
		forms (SGML, HTML, PDF, PostScript, RTF and so forth) with or
		without modification, are permitted provided that the following
		conditions are met:
	    </para>

	    <orderedlist>
		<listitem>
		    <para>
			Redistributions of source code (SGML DocBook) must retain
			the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the
			following disclaimer as the first lines of this file
			unmodified.
		    </para>
		</listitem>

		<listitem>
		    <para>
			Redistributions in compiled form (transformed to other DTDs,
			converted to PDF, PostScript, RTF and other formats) must
			reproduce the above copyright notice, this list of
			conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation
			and/or other materials provided with the distribution.
		    </para>
		</listitem>
	    </orderedlist>

	    <important>
		<para>
		    THIS DOCUMENTATION IS PROVIDED BY THE AUTHOR "AS IS"
		    AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT
		    NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF
		    MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE
		    DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE AUTHOR BE LIABLE FOR
		    ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR
		    CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES (INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO,
		    PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF
		    USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION) HOWEVER
		    CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN
		    CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING
		    NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE) ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE
		    USE OF THIS DOCUMENTATION, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE
		    POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.
		</para>
	    </important>
	</legalnotice>
	<abstract>
	    <para>
		This book provides a guide to working with XML data
		using C++ and the xmlwrapp library. It covers everything
		that will need to know to get started working with xmlwrapp.
		After reading this book, you should not have any trouble
		reading the xmlwrapp header files or using the xmlwrapp
		reference documents.
	    </para>

	    <para>
		The latest version of this book can be found at
		<ulink url="http://pmade.org/software/xmlwrapp/">http://pmade.org/software/xmlwrapp/</ulink>.
	    </para>
	</abstract>
    </bookinfo>

    <xi:include href="intro.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="quickstart.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="prepare.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="parsing.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="documents.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="node.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="attributes.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="xslt.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="whatnext.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="tips.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="license.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="bundling.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="changelog.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="todo.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="credits.xml"/>
</book>
