<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
                      "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
>
<chapter id="quickstart"><title>Building and Installing</title>
    <!--=================================================================================-->
    <section id="qs-req"><title>Requirements</title>
	<para>
	    Since xmlwrapp is a wrapper around the libxml2 parser, you will
	    need to have that library installed and working first.  libxml2 is
	    written in C and can be built on a large number of
	    platforms. libxml2 can be downloaded from its <ulink
	    url="http://xmlsoft.org/">web site</ulink>.
	</para>

	<para>
	    You may already have libxml2 installed since it is bundled with
	    many operating systems. When libxml2 is installed, a shell script
	    called <command>xml2-config</command> is installed with it. You
	    can use the <constant>--version</constant> command line option to
	    see what version of libxml2 is installed.
	</para>

	<para>
	    In order to use xmlwrapp, you need to be using at least version
	    2.4.28 of libxml2. This is due to minor API changes and bug fixes
	    that are part of each libxml2 release.
	</para>
    </section>
    <!--=================================================================================-->
    <section id="qs-compile-unix"><title>Building Under Unix</title>
	<para>
	    xmlwrapp comes with a Perl script called
	    <command>configure.pl</command>. This script will generate the
	    correct make files for your environment and compiler. This also
	    adds Perl to the previous list of requirements. It should be noted
	    that Perl is not used in any other place inside xmlwrapp except
	    this script.
	</para>

	<para>
	    In order for <command>configure.pl</command> to determine where
	    libxml2 was installed it will need to execute the
	    <command>xml2-config</command> script that was installed with
	    libxml2. If that script is not in your path you can use the
	    <constant>--xml2-config</constant> option to tell
	    <command>configure.pl</command> where it is.
	</para>

	<para>
	    The first step to building xmlwrapp is to run the
	    <command>configure.pl</command> script. It has some reasonable
	    defaults if you don't supply any command line options. To see the
	    list of possible options, try using the
	    <constant>--help</constant> option.
	</para>

	<para>
	    To help <filename>configure.pl</filename> out, you should have
	    your <constant>CXX</constant> environment variable set to the full
	    path for the C++ compiler you want to use. If you are like me, you
	    have more than one compiler installed.
	</para>

	<para>
	    After <command>configure.pl</command> has finished successfully,
	    you can run <command>make</command> and <command>make
	    install</command>. The build system should work with either BSD or
	    GNU make.
	</para>

	<example id="qs-compile-ex"><title>Using the configure.pl Script</title>
	    <screen>
<![CDATA[
perl configure.pl --prefix=/usr/local
make
make install
]]>
	    </screen>
	</example>
    </section>
    <!--=================================================================================-->
    <section id="qs-compile-mac"><title>Building Under Mac OS X</title>
	<para>
	    First, you should have <ulink
	    url="http://xmlsoft.org/">libxml2</ulink> installed. I don't
	    recommend that you download the pre-built binaries, as they are
	    too far out of date. libxml2 builds from source very nicely on
	    OSX.
	</para>

	<para>
	    xmlwrapp has been tested on OSX version 10.1.x with the April 2002
	    Developer Tools (using /usr/bin/g++ [gcc-937.2]).  Because the
	    <filename>configure.pl</filename> script is too stupid to build
	    shared libaries on OSX, you will have to disable that. Here is
	    what I do to compile under OSX.
	</para>

	<example id="qs-compile-mac-ex"><title>Mac OS X Compile Session</title>
	    <para>From a Terminal.app inside the xmlwrapp-* directory.</para>
	    <screen>
<![CDATA[
setenv CXX /usr/bin/g++
./configure.pl --disable-shared --prefix=$HOME/Local
make
make install
]]>
	    </screen>
	</example>

	<warning>
	    <para>
		Don't use /usr/bin/g++3 to compile xmlwrapp. That compiler is
		broken and does not handle exceptions correctly. If you are
		using OSX 10.2.X and the December 2002 Developer Tools, it
		should be safe to use gcc 3.1, this has not been tested yet.
	    </para>
	</warning>
    </section>
    <!--=================================================================================-->
    <section id="qs-compile-win32"><title>Building Under Windows</title>
	<para>
	    You can compile a native Windows version of the xmlwrapp library
	    by using the supplied MSVC 6 project files. The project files are
	    in the <filename>platform/Win32</filename> directory. Because of
	    problems with the standard library that comes with MSVC 6, you
	    will need to use a different implementation.
	</para>

	<para>
	    For a free high quality standard C++ library, visit <ulink
	    url="http://stlport.org/">the STLport web site</ulink>. The
	    included project files are built using MSVC 6 and the STLport
	    version 4.5.3.
	</para>

	<note>
	    <para>
		If you want to build xmlwrapp using the cygwin environment,
		you should follow the instructions for building under
		Unix. You should make sure there are no spaces in the
		directory paths for your current directory or any of your
		include or library paths.
	    </para>
	</note>

	<para>
	    If you don't have libxml2 installed on your system you should download and install binaries of
	    <ulink url="http://www.zlatkovic.com/projects/libxml/index.html">libxml2</ulink> and
	    <ulink url="http://www.zlatkovic.com/projects/libxml/index.html">iconv</ulink>.
	</para>

	<para>
	    Once you have that done, you will need to edit the project files,
	    either by hand or using MSVC, to alter the include paths so that
	    they point to the libxml2 and iconv include directories. The
	    current paths assume you have libxml2 and iconv in the same
	    directory that you have the xmlwrapp directory in.
	</para>

	<para>
	    After the project files point to the correct paths, you can
	    compile xmlwrapp. You may need to select the Release build or the
	    Debug build, depending on what you want to do. When you choose
	    "Rebuild All" from the "Build" menu, xmlwrapp and the example
	    programs should compile without any warnings or error messages.
	</para>

	<note>
	    <para>
		In order for the example programs to run, you will need to
		have the libxml2 and iconv libraries installed in a system
		path. If you don't want to do that, you can do what I do, and
		put the libraries in the <filename>Debug</filename> and
		<filename>Release</filename> folders.
	    </para>
	</note>
    </section>
    <!--=================================================================================-->
    <section id="qs-test"><title>The Test Suite</title>
	<para>
	    If you are on a platform where the
	    <filename>configure.pl</filename> script is supported, you can run
	    the xmlwrapp test suite. This is done by first enabling the test
	    suite using the <constant>--enable-tests</constant> option to the
	    <filename>configure.pl</filename> script.
	</para>

	<para>
	    You can then build the xmlwrapp library as usual with
	    <command>make</command>. Once the library is built, you can run
	    the test suite using <command>make test</command>.
	</para>
    </section>
    <!--=================================================================================-->
    <section id="qs-link"><title>Linking Your Application With xmlwrapp</title>
	<para>
	    If you are using an IDE, such as MSVC, linking with the xmlwrapp
	    library is as simple as adding the library to a dialog box
	    field. It is just as simple to link with xmlwrapp if you are
	    compiling from the command line using <command>make</command>.
	</para>

	<para>
	    When you ran <command>configure.pl</command> and then
	    <command>make install</command>, a shell script called
	    <command>xmlwrapp-config</command> was generated and installed
	    into your <filename>bin</filename> directory.
	</para>

	<para>
	    You can use this script to give the correct command line options
	    to your compiler. This includes the location of the xmlwrapp
	    header files and other libraries to link with, such as libxml2.
	</para>

	<para>
	    Here is an example, assuming that your entire application is
	    contained within a file called <filename>example.cxx</filename>
	    and the path to your compiler is stored in the
	    <constant>CXX</constant> environment variable.
	</para>

	<example id="qs-link-config"><title>Using the xmlwrapp-config Script</title>
	    <screen>
<![CDATA[
$CXX -c `xmlwrapp-config --cxxflags` example.cxx
$CXX -o example example.o `xmlwrapp-config --libs`
]]>
	    </screen>
	</example>

	<para>
	    There are other command line options that can be given to the
	    <command>xmlwrapp-config</command> script, such as
	    <constant>--version</constant>. Use the
	    <constant>--help</constant> option to get information about all
	    possible options.
	</para>
    </section>
    <!--=================================================================================-->
</chapter>
<!--
vim:ft=docbk:tw=130
-->
